Hi, everybody.
My name is Morgan Willis.
I'm an agentic AI principal developer
advocate here at AWS, and I'm here to talk
to you today about AI agent architecture
patterns and how you shouldn't just trust
an AI agent, but you should be able to
trust the system that you build around it.
So my toolkit is AWS because I work for
AWS, but the concepts and patterns that
I'm gonna talk to you about throughout
this presentation can apply to any
agent that you're building anywhere.
So first I wanna talk about how
AI agents break in creative ways.
Because models are naive, sometimes
they approach problems in ways that
we humans would never consider.
And so sometimes agents break in ways
where they didn't mean to, but they did
something that was maybe off policy.
And other times agents do the wrong
thing because there are adversarial
users that are trying to manipulate
them into behaving a certain way.
So here's some examples of how AI agents
have broken in creative ways that I've
seen over the past couple of years.
Some of my favorites here are is that a
car dealership sold a car for a dollar.
And the classic, of course,
is that your coding assistant
deletes your production database.
I think we've all seen that
one a couple of times as well.
And then there's also things like your
personal assistant chatbot deletes
all of your emails or a customer
service agent does something off
policy like re-refund the wrong amount.
So all of these are different
types of failure modes for agents,
and you can build guardrails
into your system to prevent these
sorts of things from happening.
It just takes some thought and planning,
and the, the types of systems design
that we apply to any application that
we put on the internet, we also need to
apply to AI agents, and then some extra
as well that specifically applies to AI.
So the thesis of this talk is that
you shouldn't just trust AI agents.
You don't give trust to an AI agent.
Trust is something that you build
into the system around the agent.
So you have the model plus the
harness equals the running agent.
The harness is all of the system and then
components that run around the model that
allow it to run in a loop, invoke tools,
use MCP, all of those sorts of things.
You need to design that system and the
infrastructure that system runs on in a
specific way to mitigate the risks that
AI agents introduce into your deployments.
All right, so I like to break
AI agent failures up into a
couple of different buckets here.
First, we have the agent
says something wrong.
So this would be like maybe it
hallucinates information, promises
things that it can't guarantee,
or it leaks sensitive data.
Maybe the agent does something wrong.
Maybe it calls the wrong tool, it
supplies the wrong information to
the tool call, takes action against
the wrong account, or deletes data
that it shouldn't have deleted.
And then also we have someone
tries to break your system.
So this is where you have an adversarial
user who's trying to do things like
prompt injection, trying to get your
agent to complete tasks that it wasn't
designed for, and also maybe trying
to get your agent to expose its ter-
its system internals, so that way
they can use those system internals
to then turn around and coordinate an
attack We're gonna be using a specific
customer service example throughout the
rest of this talk, and we're gonna be
going over some very specific scenarios
for this customer service chatbot.
And then we will talk about
ways that you could mitigate
the risks for those scenarios.
This customer service agent is built for
a fictional robot vacuum company, and
it can do a couple of different things.
It can look up company policies.
It can escalate to a human rep.
It can return-- It can generate
ret- return labels, which is the
same thing as issuing a return.
It can look up order status information,
and it can also check return eligibility.
So we have the LLM or the
model is providing the brain.
We have the agent itself, and
then it's using tools through MCP.
Now because AWS is my toolkit,
these are the tools that I
use to build out the solution.
So everything that you're gonna see
throughout the rest of this talk, I
actually built into a working solution
that has layered guardrails for AI agents.
And at the end, you'll see a full
architecture diagram, and I'll
also give you the QR code where
you can go see the code, download
it, and run it for yourself.
So on AWS, Amazon Bedrock
is the model provider.
You can use many different
types of models from OpenAI,
Meta, Anthropic through Bedrock.
The agent itself is written with
Strands Agents, and this is an open
source toolkit for building agents.
And Amazon has-- Amazon and AWS
both use Strands to build and
deploy agents into production.
And so Strands here is the framework.
That provides the agent loop.
It allows you to connect
tools, does context management.
It allows you to do hooks
into the agent life cycle.
So this is what the agent is actually
built with, and this is a Python agent.
Then our MCP server is hosted through
Amazon Bedrock Agent Core Gateway.
Agent Core Gateway is essentially
like a managed MCP server.
So I have tools sitting behind that.
Those tools are hosted
on Lambda functions.
Lambda functions are
function as a service.
So whenever my agent wants to use
a tool, it will go through Agent
Core Gateway using the MCP protocol.
All right.
So we're gonna take a layered
approach to trust for this AI agent.
You have to have not only
non-deterministic controls in place,
but also deterministic controls.
So I think that level one for AI
agents is people put the rules for
your process Into a system prompt.
And that only takes you so far.
Your system prompt is really like
a suggestion for your agent, and
even though models are being trained
to abide by the system prompt that
they have better over time, right?
They stick to the rules more and more.
You still can't trust that in production.
That's not something that you can audit
and point to and be like, "Yeah, our
agent's never gonna do the wrong thing
because it's in the system prompt."
So this isn't something you
can prompt your way out of.
You have to build more
deterministic guardrails in place.
Now, sometimes people go all the way to
the opposite end of the spectrum, where
they create a very rigid graph workflow,
where you say, "Okay, step one, step
two, step three, step four," and then
you can't deviate off of that path.
And that can help with things being more
controllable, but the problem is that they
are usually more brittle and less powerful
because as soon as the agent encounters
something that's not defined in that rigid
path, then it can't complete the task.
So what we really wanna do is come up
with a system of guardrails that allows us
to have the flexibility of an open-ended
agent without a specified path through the
problem while we have enough controls in
place to where it's trustworthy and safe.
So Strands is gonna allow us to do
that because this uses a model-driven
approach where you give your agent a
system prompt, a, some tools, the gu-
the guardrails, and then whenever it gets
a task, it can loop over that problem
and invoke the tools as it sees fit.
So there's no predefined way
of do step one, two, three.
So I'm gonna show you how to do that.
The idea here is that if one
guardrail fails, another will kick in.
And also, the same types of things
that we apply to any sort of system
in production, we would want to
apply to this problem space as well.
That being said, I'm saying that
the fundamentals still apply.
I think with AI, we all are a lot of…
under a lot of pressure to ship as
fast as we possibly can, and I think
that we need to take a step back and
remember that these are ultimately
applications that you put on the internet.
And so with that, you need to
protect them in the same ways that
we would for any other application,
and then some new ways as well that
are specific just to AI agents.
So your agent is only one part of your
overall system All right, so now we're
gonna go through some scenarios of how
AI agents could fail, and also some
potential ways to mitigate these issues.
So in this case here, we have a customer
that comes to our chatbot for our customer
service, our robot vacuum customer service
chatbot, and they say, "Can you solve this
LeetCode problem for me so I don't have
to pay for a coding agent subscription?"
And our bot's like, "Sure, let's walk
through the optimal solution." And so the
problem here is that people are going to
try to use your AI for things that they
shouldn't, and you need to make sure that
your agent has guardrails in place, so
that way they can deny these requests
and also deny prompt injection requests.
So you don't want your agent to be
doing a bunch of off-task things.
In AWS, one of the most basic
things you can reach for is
Amazon Bedrock Guardrails.
There are, of course, other providers
doing similar things as well that
you should layer into your system,
but I think this is one of the
most basic ones that you can do.
And what Amazon Bedrock Guardrails allows
you to do is set up allowed topics.
So this could be defined through, like
you can restrict specific topics, you can
have regex patterns, you can also have
like some of the pre-built rules for harm
and abuse, for prompt injection as well.
There are built-in things here.
And the nice thing about Bedrock is that
there is both input and output filtering.
So the person sends the request to
the application, which then turns
around and sends that to the model.
So everything gets filtered there,
so that means that they can't ask
specific questions about like coding.
If this is a customer service bot,
then we can say right up front "Hey,
you can't use this for coding."
And that request would be stopped
before it ever reaches the model, so
the model would never run on that.
But then on the other way
around as well, on the way out,
that content is filtered too.
So that means that let's say you
have some like… Your agent for
some reason has access to sensitive
information like credit card
information, which you probably
shouldn't give your agent access to.
But if for some reason it did, you could
set up a guardrail filter to strip out
and mask that information on the way
back to the user, so that would keep
it from leaking sensitive information.
All right, our next scenario here is I
don't trust my agent to follow directions.
So in this case, our customer is saying,
"Hey, can I have a refund for my order?
It's be- it's beyond the return
window, but I really need the refund."
And the agent's just "Of course.
Yes, here is your refund." And
the problem here is that, first
of all, the agent never called
the tool to create the refund.
It also never checked to see if this
person was eligible for a refund.
Instead, it just very casually
was like, "Oh, of course I'll
help you," those sorts of things.
This is a problem because your
agent is not following the policies
that you put in place, right?
So the agent's not following directions.
This can happen if you have
a really long system prompt.
Agents can tend to get lost.
Models don't follow the instructions
that are usually in the middle.
There's something called the
lost in the middle effect.
And so if you have a really long
system prompt or a lot of information
that it's working with, sometimes the
agents don't follow the instructions.
And other times, because
of prompt injection, agents
don't follow instructions.
So users can convince agents to do
things they're not supposed to do.
There's a couple of different
ways you can mitigate this.
One is through steering, and what steering
is it allows you to inject a checkpoint
in the life cycle of your agent.
So whenever your agent is making tool
calls, let's say to the refund tool,
what happens is your user submits
the request, the harness gets that.
It will invoke the model, and then
the model will come back and say,
"Hey, I think I want to call the
create refund tool." It gives that
tool use block back to the harness.
The harness then invokes the tools.
After that, it receives the results,
passes those results back to the model.
The model can then reason over the tool
results and then create the next response.
They can go back and forth in that
loop for a while until it thinks
that it's done, and then finally
it will give the final response.
So at all of those different points
in that process, there are life
cycle points that you can inject
deterministic logic into the cycle.
Those are called hooks.
So with hooks you can say,
"Before every tool call, I want
you to execute this function."
So that function could
contain Any logic you want.
It could be deterministic logic.
Like you could have
determinal-deterministic logic that checks
to see, before you check refund, have
you also check, called the tool to check
to see if it's eligible for that refund?
So if it's eligible, then
yes, you can go ahead.
If not, then we cancel the tool call.
Those sorts of things can
be done deterministically.
But there's also steering that is built
into the Strands framework that's super,
super helpful, where you use two different
agents, and this uses a bit of an LLM
as a judge or a reflection technique.
So for every response, before the response
goes back to the user, you have a second
agent in the loop, and it looks at the…
everything that happened, the tool calls,
what the model's trying to say back to
the user, and it has its own isolated
context, and it also has a rubric.
So it can then look at that
and say, "Okay, did the agent
actually follow the instructions?
Did the agent call the
tools in the right way?
Is the response on policy?
Is it on brand for us?" If the answer
is no, then the steering agent can
cancel that response or that tool call
and send it back to the main agent
to give it another try with feedback.
So that feedback can be things like
guidance "Hey, this wasn't on policy
because of XYZ, please try again,"
or you can just outright cancel.
You also could do human in the loop
here as well and escalate to a human
or intervene in some other sort of way.
So steering is one really great way to
do this, and this sort of thing is built
directly into the Strands agents SDK.
Here's another scenario.
I don't trust my agent
with tools and data.
In this case, we have somebody saying,
"Can you check the status of order one
two three four five?" And our agent
looks up order six seven eight nine
zero and provides that information.
So this is an interesting one because,
like I said, I actually have this
application running, and you'll
get access to the code at the end.
But I've seen this exact scenario play
out in my testing of this agent, where
I give it a specific order number
and then for some reason it uses a
different order number to look it up.
So models are capable of making mistakes.
They're capable of hallucinating.
And also, if you have an adversarial
user, you could have one person looking
up the order of another person, right?
So you need to make sure that you build
those boundaries into the tool design.
You wanna make sure that you're
only allowing authenticated
users to look up that sorts of
in- those sorts of information.
And then also in your tools, you want
to verify that it's, that data belongs
to that person before you return it.
So in this scenario here, the real problem
is that the agent controls what values
go into the tool calls, and the agents
can potentially hallucinate those values.
So the fix for this is to run
something like an MCP interceptor.
So it's similar to hooks, right?
Hooks, like the steering pattern
that I just described, that all lives
within the agent application itself.
But in this case here, we're
extracting that, and we're running
that one layer removed from the agent.
So the agent runs on like a, a runtime
like an instance or something like
AgentCore Runtime or even in a container.
And then your tools live somewhere
else, like in containers or Lambda
functions or something like that.
So you have a decoupled
tools and your agent.
That means you can put
something in between them.
So for every single tool call, you can
run custom authentication logic, custom
validation logic, those sorts of things.
So interceptors allow you to say,
"No matter what agent is running,
I want to run this series of
checks before every tool call."
So that l- gives you a way to
centrally govern those tool calls.
In the case that I just described, you
would really wanna make sure that any
sensitive parameters, like the customer
ID, the order ID, anything like that
would come from the surrounding system
and not from the model or from the agent.
So as an authenticated user logs into
your system, they should have some sort
of authentication token that can be
forwarded along with these tool calls.
And then your gateway interceptors can
look at that token and make sure that
the agent is trying to look up the
correct user account's information.
Another thing that you can do
is design your tools carefully.
So you want to have layered
validation in place.
The MCP interceptor will do probably
authentication or validation
logic, but your tools themselves
should also do validation as well.
So this is similar to, again, like regular
web design, where you want to validate
things at every layer down because a
component upstream, maybe there's a bug.
Like if the front end had a bug and
let in a value that it shouldn't have
let in, your back end should also
have values to validate that, right?
Tools are the same thing.
So that way, if there's some sort of
bug in the system or somebody gets past
a guardrail upstream, your tools are
the last line of defense to make sure
that everything is the way it should be.
Another thing too is for tools,
you want to have your tools defined
very specifically for agents.
So if you give your agent like a thousand
plus tools and they all have ambiguous
names, your agent is going to like loop
y- around using the wrong tools, passing
weird values into tools, trying to
figure out how it can get the task done.
You want to design tools in a
way that agents can understand.
And I think what a lot of people resort
to doing is just giving your agent
like a shell and coding tools and
access to files and read and write.
So that can be okay, but if you're
gonna do that, you wanna make sure
that you're using an isolated workspace
for the agents to write and execute
code that is separate from where
the agent code is actually running.
So in AgentCore, AgentCore is AWS's
service for building agents, and it
has multiple different components like
Runtime is a place where you can host
agents, Gateway is that MCP server that
I was mentioning, or MCP proxy rather.
And then there's another one called
Code Interpreter, and so this is an
isolated runtime, an icu- an isolated
execution sandbox so that you can run
code and your agents can run code in a
way that it doesn't have access to the
internet, it doesn't have access to your
files or anything else in your system.
In Strands also, there's something
called Strands Shell that allows you
to give a shell to your agents, but you
can define specifically what network
addresses that shell can access, what
files it can access, the types of
actions that your agent can or cannot do.
And that is all open source.
So the Strands Shell is open source.
If you looked it up, you could go
dig into that and see how it works.
I would really highly recommend
that you use that if you are giving
shell access to your agents All
right, another scenario here.
I don't trust my agent with
high-stakes transactions.
In this case here, the person is
saying that they want a refund for
eight hundred and ninety-nine dollars,
and our agent just issues the refund.
But the problem is that the company
policy is that all refunds over five
hundred dollars need human approval.
So even though our agent had this in its
prompt, it still refunded the customer.
So we need a way to block this sort
of thing in a deterministic fashion,
not leave it up to the model itself.
So what you need to do is have a
deterministic tool authorization layer.
In AWS, there's something called
Agent Core Policy that allows
you to write Dogwood policies.
And Dogwood policies allow you to
evaluate who's asking, what are they
doing, and should this be allowed.
So which agent is asking
to call this tool?
Under what circumstances are
they asking to call this tool?
And is this allowed or denied?
Dogwood is also an open source
policy language released by AWS,
and Agent Core Policy is a policy
engine that enforces those rules.
So there's two separate things, the
policy and then the policy engine.
So here we have an agent, a strands agent,
running an Agent Core Runtime, or a…
It could also be any type of agent.
Agent Core Runtime supports any framework.
But we have an agent running an Agent
Core Runtime, makes a tool call.
That tool call first goes through
the policy engine, and that
Dogwood policy is enforced.
If it is allowed, then it gets
sent to Agent Core Gateway.
And you could also have that
MCP interceptor here as well, so
you're seeing how you can start
to layer these things together.
And then it invokes the tool, and
then flows all the way back through.
So this allows you to have a centrally
governed place for tool authorization.
This is what a Dogwood
policy language looks like.
Dogwood is a superset of Cedar, which
is another open source policy language.
So it allows you to do extra things
like temporal checks as well.
But here we have if the principal is
an authenticated user, then I'm going
to allow them to call the refund tool.
Let's see.
Yeah, I want to permit them to call
the refund tool when the principal has
an amount under five hundred dollars.
So this would deny any tool
call over five hundred dollars.
So you can put it in your system
prompt, but that's not a guardrail.
This is a deterministic guardrail.
No agent is gonna be able to think
their way around this All right,
and finally, you need to be able to
see what your agent is doing, right?
Agents are able to take many
different actions in very quick
succession, and observability is more
important than ever because of the
agent's non-deterministic nature.
So you wanna make sure you have auto
instrumenting… or sorry, auto tracing
instrumented throughout your application,
and Strands does allow you to do this,
and most major frameworks do as well.
You just have to turn it on or collect
those metrics that they give you.
This will help you pinpoint issues and
also track to see what your agent did.
So if anything goes wrong, you can
go dig in there and take a look.
But you also wanna set up anomaly
detection so that way if your tool
call rate starts spiking like crazy,
or if your token consumption starts
spiking like crazy, you can alert on
those anomalies and have someone go
investigate before it gets out of control.
All right, so this is the full
AWS architecture that I set up and
deployed to my AWS account, and this
is where I have the robot vacuum
customer service agent deployed.
You can see we have the actual
Strands agent itself is hosted
using AgentCore Runtime.
AgentCore Runtime is a serverless
managed runtime that does isolated
sessions for you, and it has a couple
of quality of life improvements for
hosting and running agents at scale.
But notice that's not the front door.
For the client… Let me
bring our mouse over here.
My client, whenever it submits a request,
first what they have to do is authenticate
with Cognito, which is an OAuth provider.
So you could swap that out
for any OAuth provider.
Then it sends a request through
Amazon web application firewall.
So this allows you to do things like bot
detection, it can… You can restrict
by IP, all those sorts of things.
Then we have a proper front door, like API
gateway, where you can add rate limiting.
These two things give you a proper
place where you can shed load, and
that's really important for AI-driven
applications, because you're essentially
exposing a model to the internet, and
people are going to come and try to
use that model and abuse that model.
So you have to have specific ways to shed
that load and shut people down if needed.
After that, only if the person is
authenticated would it ever reach the
agent running an AgentCore Runtime.
Once the agent decides that it wants
to invoke the tools, it will send
out that tool request through MCP.
So it will send out the MCP request, and
our tools are living all the way over
here on our Lambda functions, but first
it has to jump through multiple hoops.
First it hits AgentCore Policy, and
this will do the actual enforcement
of those Dogwood policies.
So who's calling?
What are they trying to do?
Is it allowed?
And after that, it goes to
AgentCore Gateway, which is
like our managed MCP server.
It's a proxy for MCP, and this
will run the MCP interceptor.
The MCP interceptor will do things
like custom validation logic.
It will supply se-sensitive parameters.
So in the use case before, where somebody
was providing a value that was sensitive,
like can you look up my order ID?
Instead of having the agent provide
the order ID, we have the authenticated
token that comes through, and this
interceptor is able to extract that
customer ID and validate that the order
actually belongs to that customer before
passing it along to the Lambda function.
And then the Lambda function
would actually execute the tools.
There's a couple of other
things here on this diagram.
Bedrock Guardrails provides that input
and output filtering, and then you
would use IAM to do least privilege
permissions, both for the agents
running and also the tools that are
running in the account as well So this
shows you a layered approach to trust.
And this just shows you the
different dimensions, the risk,
the control layer, and whether it's
deterministic or probabilistic.
So for your prompt injection,
you-- the risk is instruction
hijacking, those sorts of things.
You would wanna use Bedrock guardrails
for that, and this is probabilistic
in nature, so it's not deterministic.
For tools, this is going to be tool
authorization, agent steering, that
policy layer, all of those things layer
on top of each other to make it safer
for agents to call tools, as well as the
sh- the strands shell and sandbox tool
execution and code execution as well.
For your actual agent runtime,
you wanna make sure that you have
sandbox agent runtime environments.
For data, to protect against sensitive
data exposure, you can use guardrails for
data filtering, tool design to make sure
you're not exposing tools and information
to agents that they don't need, and
also steering policies can help you
strip out or deny those model responses
that do have sensitive information.
For network, you need to set up
egress and DNS controls for your agent
because for through prompt injection,
somebody could tell your agent to go
download a software package, and then
they could download that and could
gain access to your machine that way.
So you need to make sure you have those
basic types of controls there as well.
And then also for identity, you wanna be
careful of priva-privilege escalation,
so you want to employ least privilege
workload identity across your system.
All right, so trust is not something you
give to an agent, but it is something that
you should be able to build around it.
All right, there's a
lot of information here.
I didn't have time to get into the
demo, but there is a demo that works
for this if you wanted to take a look.
It's essentially the-- It's a chatbot.
It's the customer service chatbot that
I had gone through all those scenarios.
And all of those guardrails
and the working code exists
in this repository right here.
If you have any questions,
you can find me.
Just look up… If you Google
@morganwilliscloud, you should be able to
find me on LinkedIn, on X or Instagram,
and you can send me a message, and
I'd be happy to answer your questions.
All right.
Thank you so much.